<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reviews | Arto Bendiken</title>
    <link>https://ar.to/reviews.html</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ar.to/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Reviews</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ar.to/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>Reviews</title>
      <link>https://ar.to/reviews.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Violence: Robots and Germs, Hackers and Drones</title>
      <link>https://ar.to/2015/07/the-future-of-violence.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ar.to/2015/07/the-future-of-violence.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;small&gt;Originally published as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1351021186&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;book review in my Goodreads account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disappointing overall, and at times shallow and boring. One emerges with the assessment that the two authors are easily impressed by surface-level phenomena. They maintain that narratives taught in civics class suffice to illuminate the origins and practice of politics. They perceive a simple world, where stated intentions equal actual objectives, costs can be judged relative to ostensible objectives without minding actual effects, correlation generally implies causation, and the direction of the arrow of causality can be promptly determined. These are characteristics more of a Haidtian moral matrix than the dispassionate analysis one might have wished for in a book of this kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors speak confidently about their ability to understand and predict this neatly modeled world of theirs, not particularly endeavoring to uncover their own implicit premises&amp;mdash;brief mentions of Western liberalism aside&amp;mdash;and rarely hedging or qualifying their rather confident assertions, many which could readily be challenged. In the gulf between reality and academia, this work is more a product of its environment than a root cause analysis that will stand the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, in largely restricting themselves to disruptive technologies with ETAs defined with pretty firm confidence margins, we were at least spared yet another alarmist narrative of shoddily-premised and amateurishly-informed more speculative futures, which in this instance might have been titled something like &amp;ldquo;the state v. gray goo&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the most readable part of the book is the initial bit that discusses some of the developing technologies of mass empowerment that are set to make the first half of this century an &amp;ldquo;interesting times&amp;rdquo; to live through per that purported old Chinese curse. There is nothing new here, but it is at least a useful overview of biotech terrors to come as well as the developing arms race in autonomous weaponry, soon to be wielded by state and non-state actors both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is followed, alas, by the middle portion of the book, where I suspect the authors will tend to lose readers who aren&#39;t Beltway policy wonks. These chapters are, chiefly, tedious apologia for the ostensible origins and continued existence of the state. The authors glimpse the coming sea change, but prove ultimately unable to transcend or escape the shore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost pathetically obsessed with the continuation of the authority and legitimacy of the status quo in political organization today (perhaps their jobs depend on it?), the authors even go on to disregard their own contention&amp;mdash;grounded in the myth of the social contract&amp;mdash;that the state is only a means, not an end unto itself. Their own authority bias here leads them down a garden path of motivated reasoning that is sure to not only find itself on the wrong side of history, but soon enough swept into its dust bin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors rehash elementary early modern political theory at length&amp;mdash;beginning with the Hobbesian war of all against all&amp;mdash;taking it all at face value as would any freshman. To say that this is a historically uninformed and philosophically unsophisticated analysis would only scratch the surface here, and the authors seem impossibly yet genuinely unaware of troves and generations of thinkers and scholars who advanced in leaps and bounds on everything they discuss here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might have hoped, ultimately, for a deeper nonideological and amoral (&amp;ldquo;check your morality at the door, please&amp;rdquo;) analysis premised, say, on an evolutionary and game-theoretic angle instead of this longwinded trite elaboration of the dominant political mythology du jour, consisting of little more than post-hoc rationalizations that already read akin to medieval notions of the divine right of kings. What&#39;s a little surprising is that the authors even acknowledge these being mere justifications for the Westphalian order, prompting the question of whether this ought to not be read as an extended bit of demagoguery in the Menckenian sense of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;preaching doctrines one knows to be untrue to men one knows to be idiots.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion, as it moves on to the prescriptive last third of the book, is further muddled by the authors&amp;rsquo; disregard for the precise use of language to aid in clarity of thought. Never, for instance, do they differentiate between positive liberty and negative liberty&amp;mdash;a distinction both elementary and essential&amp;mdash;which, unsurprisingly, helps lead them absurd conclusions such as that &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;mass surveillance makes us freer.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; Edward Snowden&#39;s &amp;ldquo;crime&amp;rdquo; accordingly merits a whole section in a similar vein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At root, though, unexamined and uncontested, lies the belief that, given sufficient resources, the state can, in fact, actually achieve its ostensible ends&amp;mdash;whether those ostensible ends be the provision of security as such, or the maintenance of a Tofflerian surplus order. This is a perspective uninformed by economic law and untempered by a developed intuition about spontaneous order; both being sides of the same coin, as per Hayek&#39;s dictum that &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;the curious task of economics is to demonstrate to men how little they really know about what they imagine they can design.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scarcely mentioned, for instance, are the more than trillion dollars and countless lives wasted fighting a futile War on Drugs. Other authors from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/325376&#34;&gt;Bill Lind&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/21901&#34;&gt;T. X. Hammes&lt;/a&gt; have made the case that the inability of the state, with every conceivable home court advantage that it has, to significantly hamper let alone eradicate these 4GW adversaries&amp;mdash;in this case, the drug cartels and their international distribution network&amp;mdash;perfectly showcases its impotence in credibly countering more dangerous internal and external adversaries going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the epistemic humility to limit themselves to the merely descriptive and predictive, the authors here choose to be prescriptive; too bad, only, that it is on such an axiomatically deficient and analytically shallow platform. As such, this amounts to rearranging deck chairs on the Titanic&amp;mdash;or make that SS Leviathan. The book best serves to underline the incompetence of the extended modern state apparatus to comprehend and cope with the rapidly multiplying and escalating challenges to its formerly unilateral hegemony. As Boyd would cackle, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you&#39;re not even in the game!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A case example thereof is that much of the discussion in the section on so-called &amp;ldquo;intermediate regulation&amp;rdquo; has already been obsoleted by subsequent technological developments, and that&#39;s all in the span of less than a decade past the authority they cite as the basis for their narrative here. You&#39;d never imagine the authors to have heard of these newer developments, even as events were in the process of overtaking and obsoleting their manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their conclusion, the authors tacitly acknowledge that the future is ungovernable, but go on to say that they&#39;re &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;not ready to give up on the state&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; yet. Good for them. For a deeper, more realistic, and better informed picture of the unfolding twenty-first century, pass on this and read the likes of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/8642675&#34;&gt;John Robb&lt;/a&gt; and old curmudgeon &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/325376&#34;&gt;Bill Lind&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Warrior Ethos</title>
      <link>https://ar.to/2015/03/the-warrior-ethos.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ar.to/2015/03/the-warrior-ethos.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;small&gt;Originally published as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1221653552&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;book review in my Goodreads account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a fan of Pressfield&#39;s historical fiction and as a student of military history, I was predisposed to like this short book of historical anecdotes and commentary on the warrior ethos; more&#39;s the pity that it turned out to be significantly problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, a naive reading would miss that this is ultimately an encomium to empire, deliberately and carefully selective with its facts. It can only be meant to inspire, not to inform&amp;mdash;and indeed, a clue to this end can be found in Pressfield&#39;s statement that he wrote this for &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;men and women in uniform&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. He evidently does not have an unduly high regard for the critical faculties of his audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An illustrative example right off the bat is the pathological case of sample bias that concludes the first chapter, narrated with a straight face and nary a historiographical concern, devoid any condemnation of eugenics, and demonstrating no comprehension of established human universals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Sparta, every newborn boy was brought before the magistrates to be examined for physical hardiness. If a child was judged unfit, he was taken to a wild gorge on Mount Taygetos, the mountain overlooking the city, and left for the wolves. We have no reports of a mother weeping or protesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As another point of note, when speaking of pride and honor, and judging the warrior ethos of Americans to be superior to that of their foes, Pressfield makes an obligatory mention of &amp;ldquo;enhanced interrogation&amp;rdquo; (torture) but omits any consideration of &amp;ldquo;collateral damage&amp;rdquo; (regrettable murder), the millions of victims of many long decades of empire-building. Similar bland disregard is given to the peoples vanquished by history&#39;s great conquerors and commanders&amp;mdash;this is very much a hagiography of the victors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the chapter on &amp;ldquo;The Civilian World&amp;rdquo;, one begins to suspect the author of outright demagoguery. Coming from an author who certainly knows better, how are we to understand a nakedly false assertion such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ancient Sparta and in the other cultures cited, a warrior culture (the army) existed within a warrior society (the community itself). No conflict existed between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The helots of ancient Sparta, who under pain of death toiled to feed and clothe these brave and honorable warriors, might have taken umbrage at the statement&amp;mdash;had they dared to look their masters in the eye. As it is, the word &amp;ldquo;helot&amp;rdquo; does not appear even once in this book that on the whole reads like an ode to the totalitarian glory that was Sparta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it be the case that wolves don&#39;t concern themselves with the opinions of sheep&amp;mdash;a warrior ethos for the ages if there ever was one&amp;mdash;such strategic omissions are all the more puzzling given the author&#39;s considerably more evenhanded treatment of these matters in his bestselling novel &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19047634&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gates of Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might have had a positive thing or two to say about portions of this work, but cannot be motivated to further comment given the overarching vexations and shallow pretense of history here. A true disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nexus</title>
      <link>https://ar.to/2014/02/nexus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ar.to/2014/02/nexus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;small&gt;Originally published as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/854078078&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;book review in my Goodreads account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up reading this roller-coaster of a cyberpunk thriller in one sitting. It&#39;s a fantastic debut and an impressive depiction of a plausible enough near future on the fast track to a technological singularity. To introduce a noob to transhumanism, I&#39;d prescribe &lt;em&gt;Nexus&lt;/em&gt; followed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17863&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Accelerando&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156785&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diaspora&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which should be plenty to blow anyone&#39;s mind wide open into a minor existential crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having won the Prometheus Award this previous year, it&#39;s no surprise that the themes presented in this story will resonate particularly strongly with libertarians. With the powers that be waging a doomed-to-fail War on Science to contain disruptive technologies, with agents of the state extorting, kidnapping, torturing, and murdering people for victimless crimes, and with a general populace turning a blind eye as usual to the atrocities committed ostensibly on their behalf, there&#39;s plenty here to keep a cynic happy. (The storyline in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18114057&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Influx&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; unfolds on rather parallel themes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us techies, this compelling vision of hackable wetware&amp;mdash;hackable in both senses&amp;mdash;presents hypotheticals and responsibilities of paramount import. As we&#39;ve learned the hard way over the past couple of years, our current approaches to computer security are broken on such a fundamental level that in reality the Emerging Risks Directorate would hardly need to break a sweat in their pursuit of the factory backdoors to Nexus OS; rather, they&#39;d just task the NSA with finding them a security exploit or two that would amount to the same thing. To prevent endless variations of digital dystopia facilitated by coercion technologies, we had better well and truly figure out provably secure computing in the next decade or so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Martian</title>
      <link>https://ar.to/2014/02/the-martian.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ar.to/2014/02/the-martian.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;small&gt;Originally published as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/846331504&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;book review in my Goodreads account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this in one go. Near-future hard science fiction at its finest, this is the ultimate marooned-on-an-island story&amp;mdash;where the island is a barren desert world twenty light-minutes past the horizon, and you&#39;re stuck at the bottom of its gravity well with a dwindling food and oxygen supply, no means of egress, and no possible hope of rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a fantastic yarn, and it&#39;s a credit to the author that the least plausible aspect of the story is its quaint and romantic premise that NASA, and the insolvent former superpower backing it, could afford to and would be able to land a manned mission on Mars&amp;mdash;and not just one, but five of them in a row. I&#39;ll put my chips on Elon Musk, thank you all the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be that as it may, if you appreciate man&#39;s battle for survival in the face of merciless nature and impossible odds, be sure to follow up &lt;em&gt;The Martian&lt;/em&gt; with the bona fide account of dogged, preposterous survival recounted in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/139069&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Endurance: Shackleton&#39;s Incredible Voyage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/29034&#34;&gt;Alfred Lansing&lt;/a&gt;. If we can survive what Shackleton and his men did, we&#39;ll survive Mars, too. Though it&#39;d surely help to have Mark Watney along for the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
